Liver thyroid relationship, that is
today's topic. The reason why I'm
talking about this today is because
statistically speaking about 30% of
people who have some kind of underlying
liver disease, liver dysfunction, may
also have a correlating or accompanying
thyroid dysfunction as well.
Now, the literature in the last 10,
15-ish years is starting to elucidate
that having liver disease
in a lot of cases is and can be a type
of hypothyroidism. And we've started
calling this term called liver
hypothyroidism. It's also referred to as
intrahepatic hypothyroidism as well.
So, pathophysiologically, this makes a
lot of sense because if you remember
about 80 80% of the T4 to T3 conversion,
this this occurs peripherally, meaning
not within the thyroid, but somewhere
else
um distal to the thyroid. Now, of that
80% T4 to T3 conversion, almost 60% of
that occurs within the liver itself. So,
even if your hypothalamus to thyroid
axis is working well, or even the
thyroid itself is very healthy, is very
robust, is working well, the fact that
upwards of 60% of your T4 to T3
conversion occurs in the liver tells us
that a lot of your thyroid hormone is
contingent on having a healthy liver.
Now, consider the overwhelming
prevalence of the the umbrella, the
spectrum of metabolic diseases that
exist in our Western populations, or
should I say almost worldwide now. So,
under that umbrella, we're talking about
obesity, we're talking about mash, m a s
h, which is formerly known as nash.
Think about diabetes, insulin
resistance,
all of that, metabolic syndrome. All
those things fall under this spectrum.
Now, anything in that spectrum can be a
possible contributor to having what's
known as liver hypothyroidism and/or
intrahepatic hypothyroidism. Now, just
think about the overall prevalence of
that spectrum of metabolic diseases I
just mentioned, those are all the target
populations who may be susceptible to
having this condition. From a diagnostic
standpoint, things may get a little
tricky here.
First of all, TSH is not a good marker
for identifying this condition. TSH may
be normal, it may be low-ish normal.
Now, T4 on the other hand, it might be
normal, or sometimes it may be a little
bit on the higher end of normal, which I
find somewhat interesting. Now,
this is most likely due to the
pituitary's upregulation of deiodinase
2. Now, there's and that's a
compensatory mechanism. Now, there's D1,
D2, D3. Now, principally, in states of
low thyroid activity or underactive um
thyroid conversion, deiodinase 2 tends
to get upregulated as a compensatory
mechanism because the brain says, "Hey,
I don't detect enough T3, so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to try to
increase my activity so I can provide
more raw material in hopes that you'll
produce more T3 from the raw material."
And in this this case, the raw material
is the T4. And this makes sense because
if you provide more T4, which in this
case would be the raw material in the
context of upregulating deiodinase 2,
the goal is to increase conversion of
that T4 to T3. So, obviously, T3 levels
are expected to be typically rather low,
and this would meet the criteria for
euthyroid sick syndrome, which
essentially means you have low low T3 in
the context of normal TSH and/or T4.
Additionally, since this is a state of
chronic stress, which is the liver's
being chronically stressed due to
metabolic diseases, the D3 enzyme
activity would be expected to be
upregulated. So, thus, your RT3 would be
expected to be elevated as well. So,
here's the take-home message. If you
have poor tolerance of thyroid meds,
there's a chance maybe you have some
underlying liver disease, liver
dysfunction that might be going on. Or
if you have anything under the
constellation of metabolic diseases,
again, obesity, diabetes, insulin
resistance, mash, fatty liver, whatever
you want to call it. If you drink
alcohol pretty regularly, then chances
are you may have intrahepatic
hypothyroidism at least to some degree.
And no, taking a ton of liver
supplements isn't going to magically
improve your liver and thus your
thyroid.
Instead, you're going to have to work on
treating the underlying issue, which is
the metabolic disease itself.